There's an old saying, "Just because you can't see something,
هناك قول مأثور يقول "لمجرد عدم رؤيتك للشيء
doesn't mean it's not there."
لا يعني أنه ليس موجوداً."
My work is -- it's a reflection of myself.
إن عملي -- هو انعكاس لي.
What I wanted to do is to
ما أردت فعله هو أن
show the world that the little things
أظهر للعالم كيف أن الأشياء الصغيرة
can be the biggest things.
يمكن أن تكون أكبر الأشياء.
We all seem to think that,
يبدو أننا جميعا نعتقد أنه
you know, if we look down on the ground, there's nothing there.
إذا نظرنا إلى الأرض فإنه لا يوجد شيء هناك.
And we use the word "nothing."
ونستخدم لفظة "لا شيء."
Nothing doesn't exist, because there is always something.
"لا شيء" ليس لها وجود لأن هناك دائما شيء.
My mother told me that, when I was a child,
عندما كنت طفلا كانت والدتي دائما تقول لي
that I should always respect the little things.
أنني يجب ان أحترم الأشياء الصغيرة.
What made me do this work? I shall go into my story.
ما دفعني نحو القيام بهذا العمل وهذه هي بداية قصتي٬
This all started when I was age five.
بدأ هذا كله عندما كنت في الخامسة من عمري
What made me do it? At school, I will admit this:
ما دفعني نحو القيام بهذا؟ في المدرسة٬
academically, I couldn't express myself.
سوف أعترف بأنني لم أستطع التعبيرعن نفسي أكاديميا.
So I was, more or less, classed as "nothing."
لذلك كنت أصنًّف -- إلى حدّ ما -- ک"لا شيء."
My world was seen as less.
وكان عالمي يُنظر إليه على أنه أقل.
So I decided I didn't really want to be a part of that world.
فقررت أنني لم أكن أريد أن أكون جزءا من ذلك العالم.
I thought, I need to retreat
فظننت أنني في حاجة إلى الإنسحاب
into something else.
إلى مكان آخر.
So when my mother used to take me to school,
لذلك عندما كانت والدتي تأخذني إلى المدرسة
she thought I was at school,
كانت تعتقد أنني كنت في المدرسة
and I used to do a U-turn, when her back was turned,
كنت أخذ منعطفا عندما تدير ظهرها
and run off and hide in the shed at the back of the garden.
وأركض وأختبئ في سقيفة خلف الحديقة.
Now, the one time I was in the shed,
وفي إحدى المرات كنت في السقيفة
and my mother suspected something,
فاشتبهت أمي بشيء
thinking I was at school.
وقد كانت تظنني في المدرسة.
My mother was like the woman in Tom and Jerry.
كانت أمي مثل المرأة في توم وجيري.
So you'd just see her feet.
لذلك فأنت ترى قدميها فقط.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I was hiding in the shed, like that.
كنت أختبئ في السقيفة هكذا
And all of a sudden ...
ثم فجأة...
And then I saw her legs.
ثم رأيت ساقيها.
And then she said -- grabbed me like that, because my mother was quite big --
ثم أمسكتني هكذا لأن أمي كانت كبيرة الحجم
and she lifted me up and she says,
ورفعتني وقالت:
"How come you're not at school?"
" لم أنت لست في المدرسة؟"
I told her I couldn't face it because the way
وقلت لها أنني لا أستطيع مواجهة ذلك
the teacher was treating me, ridiculing me,
بسبب الطريقة التي تعاملني وتسخر بها مني المعلمة
and using me as an example of failure.
واستخدامها لي كمثالا على الفشل
So I told her.
فشرحت لها.
At that age, obviously, I couldn't express it that way,
ولكنني وفي ذلك السن لم أستطع التعبيرعن ذلك بهذا بشكل طبعا
but I told her I didn't feel right.
ولكنني قلت لها أنني لم أشعر بالراحة.
And then she just said, "You're going back to school tomorrow."
ثم قالت لي: "ستذهب إلى المدرسة غدا."
And walked off. And I didn't expect that,
وذهبت ولم أكن أتوقع ذلك.
because I expected one of these ...
بل توقعت إحدى هذه الضربات...
But I didn't get it.
ولكن ذلك لم يحصل.
So I'm sitting there thinking.
وكنت جالسا هناك أفكر.
And as I looked down on the ground,
ونظرت أسفل مني إلى الأرض
I noticed there was some ants running around.
ولاحظت بعض النمل يمشون
And I went into this little fantasy world.
واسترسلت في خيالي
And I thought,
وسألت نفسي:
"These ants, are they looking for the queen ant?
"أهم يبحثون عن الملكة
Or do they need somewhere to live?"
أم يحتاجون إلى سكن؟"
So I thought "Perhaps,
لذلك فكرت "أنني لو
if I made these ants some apartments,
صنعت لهم بعض الشقق
they'll move in."
فسوف يسكنوها."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I did.
ففعلت ذلك.
And how I set about that, I got some splinters of wood.
وقمت بذلك عبر جلب شظايا الخشب.
And I sliced the little splinters of wood with a broken shard of glass,
وقمت بتشريح شظايا صغيرة من الخشب والزجاج
constructed this little apartment.
وشيدت شقة صغيرة.
Well it looked like a little shanty shed when I'd finished.
بدت ككوخ بشع عندما انتهيت.
But I thought, perhaps the ant won't know, it'll probably move in.
ولكنني ظننت أن النملة لن تعلم ذلك وأنها ستنتقل إليها
And so they did.
ففعلت ذلك.
That was a bit crude, at the time. And I made all these little apartments
كان البناء بسيطا في ذلك الوقت وصنعت شققا صغيرة
and little merry-go-rounds, seesaws and swings, little ladders.
وألعابا ترفيهية وسلالم صغيرة
And then I encouraged the ants to come 'round by putting sugar and things like that.
ثم شجعت النمل على الدخول إليها عبر وضع السكر وما شابه
And then I sat down and all the ants came along.
ثم جلست وأتى النمل
And all I could hear was "Is this for us?"
وكل ما سمعته هو: "أهذا لنا؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I say, "Yes, they're all for you."
فقلت "نعم هذا كله لكم"
And they moved in, and decided not to pay me any rent.
فسكنوها وقرروا عدم دفع الإيجار(ضحك)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And from there I was watching this little world.
وهنالك راقبت هذا العالم الصغير
It became part of me.
فأصبح جزءا مني.
When I discovered that I had this gift,
عندما اكتشفت هذه الموهبة لدي
I wanted to experiment with this world
أردت القيام بتجارب في هذا العالم
that we can't see.
الذي لا يمكننا رؤيته.
So I realized that there was more to life
فلاحظت أن هناك الكثير في هذه الحياة
than just everything that we see around us that's huge.
إلى جانب ما نراه حولنا من أشياء كبيرة.
So I started to educate myself on this molecular level.
فبدأت بتعليم نفسي على هذا المستوى الجزيئي
And as I got older, I continued. I showed my mother.
واصلت هذا العمل مع كبري في السن وعندما أريته لأمي
My mother told me to take it smaller.
قالت لي أن أصغره بعد
Now I shall show you something here.
سوف أريكم شيئا
And I'll explain.
وأشرح لكم.
As you can see,
كما ترون
that's a pinhead.
هذا رأس دبوس.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now that is called the Huf Haus.
ذا هو بيت "هوف."
The gentleman who commissioned me to do this
السيد الذي كلفني بصنع هذا
was a gentleman called Peter Huf.
اسمه "بيتر هوف."
And he says to me "Willard, can you put my house on a pinhead?"
وقال لي: "ويلارد... أتستطيع أن تضع بيتي على رأس دبوس؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I say, "How are you going to fit in there?"
فقلت له: "كيف ستسع فيه؟"
And then he said to me,
ثم قال لي:
"I don't believe you can do it. Can you really do it?"
"لا أظنك قادرا على عمل هذا...أتستطيع فعل هذا؟"
And I says, "Well, try me."
فقلت له: "جربني."
And then he said, "But I don't believe that you can do this." So I said, "OK."
ثم قال لي"ولكني لا أظنك قادرا على عمل هذا" فقلت له: "طيب."
So, to cut a long story short,
بإختصار
I went home, went underneath the microscope,
ذهبت إلى بيتي إلى تحت المجهر
and I crushed up a piece of glass,
وقمت بسحق قطعة زجاج
crushed it up.
وسحقتها.
And underneath the microscope
وتحت المجهر
there were splinters of glass.
كانت هناك شظايا الزجاج
Some of them were quite jagged.
كانت بعضها وعرة
So I was crushing up these pieces of glass,
وقمت بسحق قطع الزجاج هذه
which, as you can see,
والتي كما تلاحظون
that's the actual frame of the house.
تشكل هيكل البيت
And the actual roof is made up of a fiber,
وأما السقف فهو مصنوع من ألياف
which I found in my sister's old teddy bear.
وجدتها في دمية دب أختي القديمة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I got the teddy bear and I said,
أخذت الدب وسألتها:
"Do you mind if I pull out one of your fibers?"
"أتمانعين أخذي لإحدى أليافك؟
So I did.
ففعلت ذلك.
And I looked at it beneath the microscope. And some of it was flat.
ونظرت تحت المجهر وكانت بعضها مسطحة
So I decided to slice these up
فقررت تشريح هذه
with the tool that I make
باستخدام الأدوات التي صنعتها
by -- I sharpen the end of a needle into a blade.
كشحذ طرف إبرة ليصبح شفرة
And then I actually
ثم
slow down my whole nervous system.
أقوم بتبطيئ جهازي العصبي.
And then I work between my heartbeat,
ثم أعمل بين نبضات قلبي.
I have one-and-a-half seconds
وعندي ما يعادل الثانية والنصف
to actually move.
لأتحرك.
And at the same time I have to watch I don't inhale
ويجب علي أن أكون حذرا ألا أستنشق
my own work, at the same time.
عملي في ذات الوقت.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Because that has happened to me.
لأن هذا حصل لي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So what I did, like I said, come back to the glass.
رجوعا إلى موضوع الزجاج
I found these little bits of glass.
وجدت بعض القطع الصغيرة
And I had to make them square.
وكان علي أن أجعلها مربعة الشكل
So I'm thinking "How can I do this?"
وتساءلت عن كيف يمكن أن أفعل هذا
So what I did, I got an oilstone. Broke the edge of an oilstone off.
فجلبت حجر الصقل وكسرت حافتها
And what I did, I took pieces of glass. And I started to rub them.
ثم أخذت قطع الزجاج وبدأت بفركها عليها
I used a little tweezer which I made from a hair clip.
واستخدمت الملقط الصغير الذي كنت قد صنعته من مشبك للشعر
And I built rubber around the end of the tweezer so it wouldn't crush the glass.
وركبت المطاط على طرفي الملقط لكي لا أكسر الزجاج
And then I started rubbing, very very gently,
ثم بدأت بفرك الزجاج بلطف شديد
till some of the edges were quite square. And then I constructed it.
حتى أصبحت بعض الحواف مربعة الشكل ثم شيدتها.
And how I constructed it,
أما عملية التشييد
is by making grooves in the top of the pinhead.
فكانت عبر صنع أخاديد في أعلى الإبرة.
And then pushing the glass in with its own friction.
ثم ضغط الزجاج فيها باستخدام احتكاكها
And as I was doing it, what happened?
وبينما كنت أفعل ذلك٬
The instrument that I used turned into a catapult.
ما حصل هو أن الأداة التي كنت أستخدمها تحولت إلى مقلاع
And it went like this ...
وجعلت تفعل هكذا...
And then that was it.
وهذا ما حصل...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Gone.
اختفى.
So I'm thinking, "Mr. Huf isn't going to be very happy
فقلت لنفسي أن السيد "هوف" لن يكون سعيدا
when I told him his house has gone to another,
حين أخبره بأن بيته أصبح في مكان اخر
into the atmosphere somewhere."
في الجو.
So to cut the story short,
لإختصار القصة
I decided that I had to go back and do it.
قررت أن أعود وأبدأ من جديد
So I found some more. And I decided to, sort of,
فوجدت المزيد وقررت
construct it very, very slowly,
تشييد البيت ببطء شديد
holding my breath, working between my heartbeat,
مع حبس نفسي والعمل بين نبضات قلبي
and making sure everything is leveled.
والتأكد من أن كل شيء مستوٍ.
Because it's such a small sculpture,
ولأن المنحوتة صغيرة جدا
nothing can go wrong.
فهذا يعني أنه ليس هناك مجال للخطأ.
And I decided to build it up.
وقررت تشييده
Then I used fibers out of my jumper,
ومن ثم استخدمت أليافا من سترتي
which I held and stretched.
وقمت بمسكها ومطّها
And made the beams going around the house.
لصنع الأضلاع التي تحيط بالبيت.
And the actual windows and the balcony
أما النوافذ والشرفات
had to be sort of constructed.
فوجب بناؤها.
I used a money spider's web
فاستعملت نسيج العنكبوت
to actually attach certain things,
لربط بعض الأشياء
which sent me insane.
مما دفعني للجنون...
But I managed to do it.
لكنني تمكنت من القيام بذلك.
And when I finished it, I came back the next day.
عندما انتهيت من ذلك عدت في اليوم التالي
I noticed that the house was occupied.
ووجدته قد احتُلّ.
Have we ever heard of a dust mite?
هل سبق وسمعتم بِسوسة الغبار؟
Darren dust mite and his family moved in.
"دارين" سوسة الغبار انتقل إلى البيت مع عائلته.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So basically I'd completed the house.
على أية حال اكملت البيت
And there you are.
و... ها هو.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Right. As you can see,
نعم... كما ترون٬
Bart Simpson is having a little argument.
"بارت سيمبسون" يواجه نزاع صغير
I think they're arguing about the space on the pin.
أظن أنهم يتنازعون بشأن المساحة على الدبوس
There's not enough room for the two of them.
ليس هناك مساحة كافية لكليهما
So I didn't think he was going to throw Bart off.
لا أعتقد انه سيلقي ﺒ"بارت"
I think he was just warning him actually.
بل أظن أنه يحذره فحسب.
But this one was made out of a nylon tag
هذا مصنوع من علامة النايلون
out of my shirt.
من قميصي.
What I did, I plucked the tag out
ما فعلته هو أنني انتزعت العلامة
and put it underneath the microscope.
ووضعته تحت المجهر.
I used the needle which has got a slight blade on the end.
ثم استخدمت إبرة لها نصل بسيط عند طرفها
Can anybody see the blade on the end of that needle?
هل يستطيع أحد رؤية النصل في طرف الإبرة؟
Audience: No.
الجمهور: لا.
WW: So what I did is the same process where I
وما فعلته هو نفس العملية
just kind of hold my breath
وهي حبس نفَسي
and just work away very, very slowly,
والعمل ببطء شديد...
manipulating the plastic, cutting it, because it behaves different.
التلاعب بالبلاستيك وقصه لأنه يتصرف بطريقة مختلفة
Whenever you work on that level, things behave different.
كلما تعمل على هذا المستوى فإن الأشياء تتصرف بطريقة مختلفة
Because it's on this molecular level things change
لأن الأشياء تتغير على هذا المستوى الجزيئي
and they act different.
وتتصرف بطريقة مختلفة
And sometimes they turn into little catapults and things go up in the air.
وأحيانا تتحول إلى مقاليع صغيرة وتتطير الأشياء في الهواء
And, you know, all different things happen.
وتحدث أشياء مختلفة.
But I had to make a little barrier, going around it, out of cellophane,
وكان علي صنع حاجز صغير من السيلوفين حوله
to stop it moving.
لمنعه من التحرك
Then static electricity set in.
ثم تدخلت الكهرباء الساكنة
And it went ...
وفعلت هكذا...
And I'm trying to remove it. And the static is interfering with everything.
وأنا أحاول إزالتها ولكنها أخذت تتدخل في كل شيء
So there is sweat dripping off my head,
والعرق الذي يتقطرمن جبهتي
because I have to carve Homer Simpson like that, in that position.
لأن علي أن أنحت "هومر سيمبسون" في هذا الشكل.
And after I've cut out the shape,
وبعد قطع الشكل
then I have to make sure that there is room for Bart's neck.
يجب التأكد من ترك مجال كافٍ لرقبة "بارت".
So after I've done the same thing,
وبعد فعل الشيء نفسه
then I have to paint it.
علي طلاؤه.
And after I've actually sculpted them,
وبعد نحتهما
I have to paint them.
علي أن أطليهما...
I experimented with a --
قمت ببعض التجارب --
I found a dead fly.
وجدت ذبابة ميتة
And I plucked the hair off the fly's head.
ونتفت شعرة من رأسها
Decided to make a paintbrush.
وقررت صنع ريشة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I would never do it to a living fly.
لكني لن افعل ذلك لذبابة حية أبدا
Because I've heard a fly in pain.
لأني سمعت ذبابة تتألم
And they go "Meow! Ow!"
وكان صوتها هكذا: "أوووووو! أوو!"
Even though they get on our nerves,
حتى وإن كانت مزعجة لنا٬
I would never kill an insect
فأنا لن أقتل حشرة أبدا
because, "All creatures great and small" --
لأن "المخلوقات كلها٬ صغيرها وكبيرها"--
there is a hymn that says that.
هناك ترنيمة تقول ذلك.
So what I decided to do
فما قررت فعله
is to pluck fine hair out of my face.
هو أني نتفت شعرة ناعمة من وجهي
And I looked at it underneath the microscope.
ونظرت إليها تحت المجهر
That was the paintbrush.
فكانت هذه هي الريشة.
And whilst I'm painting I have to be very careful,
وبينما أنا أدهن يجب أن أنتبه
because the paint starts to turn into little blobs.
لأن الطلاء يبدأ بالتحول إلى فقاعات صغيرة
And it starts to dry very quickly.
ويبدأ بالجفاف بسرعة
So I have to be very quick.
فيجب أن أكون سريعا.
If I'm not, it will end up looking
إذا لم أفعل ذلك--
not like what it's supposed to look like.
فقد لا يبدو مثل المراد
It could end up looking like Humpty Dumpty or somebody else.
بل قد يبدو مثل (هامبتي دامبتي) او شخصية اخرى مختلفة.
So I have to be very very careful.
فيجب أن ألزم الحذر الشديد.
This one took me approximately,
هذا استغرق انهاؤه
I would say, six to seven weeks.
من ست إلى سبع أسابيع.
My work, rough estimate,
تقديريا٬ عملي
sometimes five, six to seven weeks;
يستغرق من خمس إلى ست إلى سبع أسابيع.
you can't always anticipate.
لا يمكنك أن تتوقع ذلك دائما. هذا العمل مضن جدا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
As you can see,
كما ترون
that's Charlton Heston brought down to size.
هذا "تشارلتون هستون" بعد تصغير حجمه
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He says to me, "Willard" --
يقول لي "ويلارد"--
You can see him saying, "Why me?"
يمكنكم أن تروه يقول: "لم أنا؟"
I says, "I enjoyed your film. That's why."
فأجيب "لأنني استمتعت بمشاهدة فيلمك٬ وهذا هو السبب."
As you can see, there's an aphid fly there.
كما ترون هناك منّة في الصورة
That's just to show the scale
والغاية هي معرفة القياس
and the actual size of the sculpture.
والحجم الفعلي للمنحوتة.
I would say it probably measures ...
قد يبلغ قياسها
a quarter of a millimeter.
ربع مليميتر.
In America they say a period stop.
في أميركا يسمونها علامة الوقف
So say if you cut a period stop in half,
لذا إن قطع علامة الوقف إلى نصفين
a full stop, that's about the size of the whole thing.
أو النقطة٬ فذلك هو حجم المنحوتة
It's made -- the chariot is made of gold.
وهي مصنوعة -- العربة مصنوعة من الذهب
And Charlton Heston is made of a floating fiber,
و"تشارلتون هستون" مصنوع من ليفة تطفو
which I took out of the air.
أخذتها من الهواء.
When the sunlight comes through the window you see these little fibers.
عندما تدخل أشعة الشمس من النافذة ترى الألياف الصغيرة
And what I normally do is walk 'round a room --
وما أفعله عادة هو أني أمشي في الغرفة
(Laughter) --
(ضحك)
trying to find one. And then I put it underneath the microscope.
وأحاول أن أجد واحدة٬ ثم أضعها تحت المجهر.
I remember one time I was doing it, and the window was open.
أتذكر أني في إحدى المرات كنت أفعل ذلك وكانت النافذة مفتوحة
And there was a lady standing by the bus stop.
وكانت هناك إمرأة واقفة بجانب محطة الباص
And she saw me walking around like this.
ورأتني أمشي هكذا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then she looked at me.
وأخذت تنظر إلي.
And then I went ...
ففعلت هكذا...
And then she went, "Hmm, OK, he's not mad."
فاطمأنت وقالت لنفسها "حسنا٬ هذا الرجل ليس بمجنون."
Yeah, to actually do this thing --
نعم... للقيام بهذا العمل --
the actual chariot is made of gold.
العربة نفسها مصنوعة من الذهب.
I had a 24-karat gold ring.
كان عندي خاتم ذهب عيار ٢٤ قيراط
And I cut off a little flake of gold.
فقشرت رقاقة صغيرة من الذهب
And I bent it 'round,
وقطعتها ثم طويتها بشكل دائري
and made it into the chariot.
وصنعت منها العربة
And the horse is made from nylon.
والحصان مصنوع من النايلون
And the spider's web is for the reins on the horse.
وخيط العنكبوت لعنان الحصان.
To get the symmetrical shape of the horse
كان الحصول على الشكل المتناسق للحصان
was very difficult,
صعبا جدا
because I had to get the horse to rear up
لأنه حصان ركوب فأردت أن يكون متبخترا
and look as though it was in some kind of action.
وأن يبدو وكأنه في نوع من الإنفعال.
When I did this one,
عندما صنعت هذا
a gentleman seen it and said to me,
رآه سيدا وقال لي:
"There's no way you can do this, you must have used some kind of machine.
"أنك صنعت هذا لوحدك هو أمر مستحيل، لا بد أنك استخدمت آلة من نوع ما.
There's no way a man can do that.
لا يمكن لرجل أن يصنع هذا٬
It must be a machine."
لا بد أن هذا من صنع آلة."
So I says, "OK then, if you say it's a machine ..."
فقلت له: "طيب إذا. إن كنت تقول أنها آلة..."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
That one took me approximately six weeks.
هذا استغرق انهاؤه ستة أسابيع.
The most famous statue in the world.
أشهر تمثال في العالم.
This one, I would say,
أود أن أقول أن هذه
was a serious challenge.
كانت تمثل تحديا كبيرا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Because I had to put the torch on the top.
لأنه كان علي وضع شعلة على الرأس
That one is, more or less, the same type of process.
ولهذه كانت عملية الصنع هي ذاتها إلى حد ما.
The bottom of it is carved from a grain of sand,
الجزء الأسفل منحوت من حبة رمل
because I wanted to get a bit of the stone effect.
لأني أردت الحصول على شكل حجري
I used a microscopic shard of diamond
واستخدمت قشرة ماسٍ مجهرية
to actually carve the actual base.
لنحت القاعدة.
Well, I can look at this one and I can be very proud of this,
ويمكنني أن أنظر إلى هذا وأن أكون فخورا جدا
because that statue has always sort of
لأن هذا التمثال كان دائما
kept an image in my head of, you know,
يمثل في رأسي
the beginning of people coming to America.
البداية للناس القادمين إلى أميركا.
So it's sort of Ellis Island, and seeing America for the first time.
فكانت هذه هي جزيرة "إليس" وكانت هي بمثابة رؤية أميركا للمرة الأولى
And that's the first thing they saw.
وكانت هي أول ما يرونه
So I wanted to have that little image.
فأردت أن يكون لدي هذا الرمز
And this is it.
وهذا هو.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And we all know that is the Hulk.
ونحن نعلم جميعا من هو اﻟ"الهَلْك"
I wanted to create movement in the eye of a needle.
أردت أن أصنع الحركة في عين إبرة.
Because we know we see needles,
لأننا نعلم ما هي الإبر
but people aren't familiar with the eye of a needle
ولكن الناس لا يعرفون عن عين الإبرة
apart from putting a thread through it.
إلا أنه لتمرير الخيط.
So I broke the needle.
فكسرت الإبرة
And made a needle look like
وجعلتها تبدو
the Hulk's broken it.
وكأن اﻟ"الهَلْك" هو من كسرها.
It's -- I had to make little holes
كان علي أن أصنع ثقوبا صغيرة
in the base of the needle, to shove his feet in.
في أسفل العين لغرز رجليه فيها
So most of my work, I don't use glue.
لذلك في معظم عملي لا أستخدم الغراء.
They go in with their own friction.
فإنها تنغرز بفضل إحتكاكها
And that's how I managed to do it.
وهكذا تمكنت من القيام بذلك.
As you can see, he's looking at the moment. He's got a little grimace on his face.
فهو كما ترون يحدق ولديه تكشيرة على وجهه
And his mouth must be probably about
وفمه على الارجح
three microns.
يبلغ ثلاث ميكرونات
So the eyes are probably about one micron or something.
فالأعين تبلغ ميكرونا واحدا على الارجح.
That ship there,
هذه السفينة
that's made from 24-karat gold.
مصنوعة من ذهب عيار ٢٤ قيراط
And I normally rig it with the web of a money spider.
عادة أقوم بصنع لباس السفينة من خيوط العنكبوت
But I had to rig it with strands of glue.
لكني اضطررت لصنعه من خيوط الغراء
Because the web of the spider, it was sending me insane,
لأن خيوط العنكبوت دفعتني إلى الجنون
because I couldn't get the web to move off.
لأني لم أستطع التلاعب بحركتها.
And that's 24-karat gold. And it's constructed. I built it.
وهذه من ذهب عيار ٢٤ قيراط مشيّدة٬ بنيتها
Constructed each plank of gold.
وشيدت كل لوح من الذهب
And the whole thing is sort of symmetrical.
والمنحوتة لها شكل متناسق
The flag had to be made out of little strands of gold.
وأشرعة السفينة مصنوعة من خيوط صغيرة من الذهب
It's almost like doing a surgical operation to get this thing right.
وكأنها عملية جراحية للحصول على النتيجة المرجوة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
As you can see, dressage.
كما ترون٬ الفروسية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's something I wanted to do just to show how I could get the symmetrical shape.
أردت أن أفعل هذا فقط لإظهار قدرتي في الحصول على شكل متناظر.
The actual rigging on the reins on the horse
أما جهاز عنان الحصان
are made from the same sort of thing.
فهو مصنوع من المادة نفسها
And that was done with a particle from my shirt.
وهي من جسيم من قميصي
And the pinhead I've made green around there
وجعلت رأس الدبوس أخضر اللون
by scraping the particles off a green shirt
عن طريق كشط الجسيمات من قميص أخضر
and then pressed onto the needle.
وضغطها على الدبوس.
It's very painstaking work,
إنه عمل مضني بشدة،
but the best things come in small packages.
لكن أفضل الأشياء تأتي في حزم صغيرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Bruno Giussani: Willard Wigan!
برونو غوساني: ويلارد ويغان!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)